[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so it's, it's the last step.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the advantage of being a dharmakārī?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, your base, your base is without you.
It keeps you in focus.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means, basically, you have spiritual powers for both spiritual and moral.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, it's really concerning, what it seems to be actually concerning is, it seems to get into spiritual powers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it's strange to be talking about death.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, what it is, is the dying energy, breathing, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The amounts of peaceful faces.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibly termination of the body,
[SPEAKER_00]: The composure is based on God.
[SPEAKER_00]: The things with composure, through that composure, you get a real mastery of the body, of the spirit, of the thought, of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you realize, it's a bit of all the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: These four bases of potency, motivation, pathways, and upgrades.
[SPEAKER_00]: In these evolutionary stages, the spiritual basis for potency, the basis for spiritual power, possessing,
[SPEAKER_00]: Composure, purity, desire, and the determinations of life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, my, many things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, my desire will neither be satisfied, nor can it help.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be neither constituted internally, nor obstructed externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: It allows perceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: After, and before.
[SPEAKER_00]: As before, so as then.
[SPEAKER_00]: As after, so before.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the door is open, the path shall be known.
[SPEAKER_00]: As day comes by day, so it might, so it might, so by the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as you can, as you can see from there, basically, it's like the, the ultimate clear perspective that is, that the mind is composed upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, I mean, the approach there is really part of this, but obviously, it ends in the same thing of like an establishment of mind on a certain
[SPEAKER_01]: Clarity that depends on a certain generality of that mindfulness in the level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says that for some people, establishing the mind in such manner would also result, as others, so to say, if there is an opening, or as the Tanisha was translating, would result in gaining these powers, or potencies.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they are basically gained on the foundations of that clear perspective that's actually the foundation of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody develops wisdom in the right manner, plus has these openings, they'll get these special powers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if somebody aims at the special powers through gaining wisdom, well, you'll have to go through developing that wisdom and knowledge based on the clear perspective, and then the powers will be secondary, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know.
Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: This whole... this whole thing is about...
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it doesn't have to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because you have one goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the other goal?
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, we use this Buddha's teaching as a way of succeeding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, perspective and wisdom will help you with whatever, but, obviously, it's not... it's not the end of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because it really talks about the determination of striving, in terms of getting rid of the question of what is wrong and what is right.
[SPEAKER_00]: With that... with that, there's been a couple of books I've designed, a couple of days of investigation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes on.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, definitely, the... the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The determination of striving, what seems to basically be the energy, is the main factor of... very much among the main factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that constant, unrelenting effort that the mind's putting in.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically how the world gets done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think I told you that before.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is a...
[SPEAKER_01]: closest to a method of practicing the dhamma, that would be the method of just not resting mentally, as in constantly striving mentally to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not striving blindly to some mechanical sort of repetition of some motions, but striving mentally to clear out the mind from unwholesome states, whether you're sitting, walking, standing, or laying down, whether
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, no matter what you're doing, externally, internally, the mind maintains the same composure and the same attitude, which is not to tolerate anything wholesome and understand the wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, as the Buddha said, unlike the monk, like the one who's a king, he doesn't leave anything out.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't leave anything
[SPEAKER_01]: Until things become very, very clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the other stimuli, the butcher, skilled butcher, cutting up a cow.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, in the beginning, you just see this mass, sort of, of organs and stuff, but the skill butcher is capable of cutting it all out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as he's cutting it bit by bit, he's understanding what those phenomena are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that needs to be qualified.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's understood in that mindful, phenomenological way, not in an analytic way, as in, you divide into 16 components and memorize them, and suddenly you think, that's not understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just collecting information.
[SPEAKER_01]: Studying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so in the proper sense, you basically keep pushing things until the clarity is reached.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always having a goal in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there's one goal in mind, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's my daughter, I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: You didn't know it was going to be, right, in this way, without it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to get some... some degree of... of understanding in order to... Well, as the suttas say, again, you... you hear the teaching and you measure the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically means you get the idea of what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you arouse energy for doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, that's why many people can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're very keen, very inspired, but they can't get the energy because they don't really know what they're supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they jumped from one meditation technique to the other, from one teach to the other, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: Deep inside, they really don't know, for themselves, what they're supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as that's the case, they won't have the energy to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you have to have something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's better than poking, or something better than... Well, initially, yeah, but you want to... you don't want to be depending on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to be depending on something poking you, you want to be poking yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And basically,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is the energy going in that now.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sure, but no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, more particularly, as in, like, if you're sitting around, don't let your mind wander into thinking lazy thoughts, but pick up something you haven't understood, something you think you understand, whatever, and just keep drilling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it will pick itself up.
[SPEAKER_01]: The momentum will take over, but not before you invest enough of, sort of, uh, winding up.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody has a bit of a sense of urgency for ages, it's going to leak into the method.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I guess so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it can.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can become a compulsion, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to die for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is there for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That has been mentioned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I mean, yeah, but then that is just like... that's your own doing, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because no matter how comfortable or
[SPEAKER_01]: I agree about circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, the fact is, well, you're still subject to death, illness, dissolution, everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just have to be thinking about those things, and you will be coming out of complacency soon enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's that lazy attitude, mental laziness, indulgence, complacency, that prevents you, or rather, takes you away from thinking those thoughts, and then you learn... And the further away you go, the harder it becomes to think those thoughts, because then you have to make more effort to think them.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I'm learning as a musician, he says, he's a musician through the years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the thing is, yeah, especially in the beginning, you might be genuine isolates and so on, but even not too bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the end of the world, even if you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as you're... as long as you're starting and doing it for the right reasons and along the right lines, as in, you're really trying to understand the suttas, not just being, in that case, sort of, picking up some metal and becoming a robot, or something, and then get completely obsessed with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's just this... so it has to be... that's why I say it's not a method, so you can't just keep repeating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't do it the same every day, because different things arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: in your experience, which means you need to look at them differently, you need to...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that which is in common to your efforts is that desire to understand, desire to reach the clarity of the phenomena, of the feeling, intention, perception, basically suffering and freedom from it, the Four Noble Truths, whatever you want to call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... if you're doing it rightly, you will
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to do too much of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you might get tired, so you can't keep actively making effort to understand, but the state of not making the effort mentally, does not need to lead to the state of being lax and complacent either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you don't have to be actively pursuing, but you can remain mindful and you can't have too much of that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when people don't see that one.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that they make too much effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when they stop making the effort, they don't stay on that mindfulness, which is neutral, then they go completely the opposite way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I made the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I get too relaxed because of the effort they made.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to find... you need to learn how to... how to... how to rest, because it is a restful place.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the mindfulness, not in distraction, not in the senses, not in the sensuality, which is usually what people use for a resting place of their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I've been working hard, now I want to put my feet up and really, you know, have a drink and just relax or go out with a friend or do something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what relaxes people, that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, that's not relaxing at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, for the mind who who has that as a starting point, it will take some effort into re-learning what true relaxation is, which is basically mindfulness, the practice of mindfulness, which is nothing other than samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're not actively pursuing the understanding of the meaning, but you remain on that basis upon which the understanding of the meaning occurs,
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why even if you're not actively pursuing it, development of that basis, of that samādhi, will bring the clarity eventually, at a slower rate, but still.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the composure, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the thing, like, to make too much effort or too little effort, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will vary on your energy every day, what you actually have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no excuse for being non-mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely, there is no excuse for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no excuse for allowing your mind to rest on unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because not resting on unwholesome things, it's not actually tiresome at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the assumption of sensuality that requires us to... well, that sort of makes us or maintains the belief that resting is when you get the pleasure of the senses or distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that takes time to unlearn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so you don't want to be
[SPEAKER_01]: Jumping and strangling a car in terms of trying to control it, nor do you want to be looking completely elsewhere where you don't even see a car.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, that's that's the whole point of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Giving that perspective where you can see it without actually having to chase it or hold it down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, no matter how tired you are physically or mentally, mindfulness is never a cause of that tiredness, nor can ever be an impediment to rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's already quite an awesome way of resting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're established upon mindfulness correctly, you can never kind of veer off too much off the right track.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can't get too wound up and restless, nor can you get too careless and sensual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, before and after what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you don't have to do anything specifically before and after.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just what's here now, but what has been, if you think about the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: What will be, if you think about the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all already present in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as before, so after.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what he clearly understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: As after, so before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, when you just be thinking about contemplating, it will be difficult to clear yourself.
Ultimately.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see for a second, before,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sure, but it's not a particular... you don't pick up particular things of your past, and then you think about it and learn from it, like deduce some sort of information that can help you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, yeah, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this refers to the actual framework of before, framework of after, on a very general level of that perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's listed there with those things, not like with things just remember what you've done, remember what you might do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before and after.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as there is now, there will be before.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as there is now, there will be after.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like that they're all three at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like before, now and after.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why is this coming?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because all the assumptions, they are assumed in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of all the habits that are existing for the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are presently present.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like when Arahant becomes another Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when he thinks of himself in the time when he was put to jhāna, even that is not his self anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't even take the past self as his self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he has presently understood the nature of self as truly not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same thing before.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the framework of the book.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same framework of after.
[SPEAKER_01]: As after, same before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You apply that perspective, apply to that perspective, in all directions, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just right here, right now, to what I'm seeing, what I'm hearing, what I'm mindful of, but any thoughts of past, any thoughts of future, everything becomes included in that perspective, clearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because you obviously have that thought for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will, always, always, always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every point of view, as Nirmala said, has like either under-determined or over-determined aspect to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, depending how you're looking, you're either looking to... What?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're either seeing your past through your present, or you're looking at the future through your present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you have some thoughts with you now, which basically are kind of lingering from something that was before.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is also present.
[SPEAKER_01]: As before, now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, you think the body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: The authentic two parts are, again, not to be taken as analytical parts that you bring together, but as actually phenomena upon which your experience of the body depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can take one part, you have to take 32.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you take all the parts that were there that can be taken, you'll have 32.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is, the body as a whole, the experience of the body as a whole, you don't leave anything out, up or down, left or right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any ideas?
[SPEAKER_01]: Spatially, you don't leave anything out in regards to that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is dependent upon that body, which is included by including that body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he dwells... dwells... Yeah, he dwells not resting upon anything, not picking up anything, not assuming anything, not taking up anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the... spatially and in terms of temporally, before or after, in terms of time,
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's a space above or below in regard to this, before or after in regard to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thing, really, just pertains to two different phenomena, but the same entity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what David's talking about, that it's like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: We do various things based on thoughts, and we see that there's this contingency to design, direction, direction, following,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be really strong.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the mind, the spirit, and the mind, you can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, not pointing at anything, not resting at anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Luminous all around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, basically, not picking up anything in any direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not going back to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just saying that you can use the word luminous, but you have to explain what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: In what sense it's luminous.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in a sense, as I said, it's in a sense, it's a non-indicative thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you just read luminous all around, you think of consciousness being this bright light that shines
[SPEAKER_01]: And that you enter in this astral plane of permanent light and beauty, or something like that, is up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just really doesn't indicate anything, anywhere, before or after, up or down, as a resting point, as a sense of self, as a something you will lean on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, that infinity of that structure, yeah, shines, you know, everywhere and nowhere, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there any evidence of deception?
[SPEAKER_00]: The light is well grasped.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think the door is well resolved.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this way, if the door is open, then the mind can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, again, there appear, you know, the phenomena of light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in fact, the light is negative in regard to everything that you see, when the light is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't see anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no light.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you're seeing is not the light.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, more particular things revealed by their light.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, it's the same principle of a more general phenomena upon which you establish your mind, because of which you don't... you then transcend the particular phenomena that depend theoretically upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything you see depends upon light being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in a sense, yeah, the absence of light.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you resolve upon perception of day and perception of light, and then your mind can develop, get established upon that perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that establishment provides you, basically, freedom from the pull of any particular things that you perceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the view is thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, just maintain the same attitude, regardless of what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, depending on what you're doing, means you will have more... you will be able to invest more or less effort in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if you're doing something
[SPEAKER_01]: It requires most of all of your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that sense, you still won't have to compromise the mindfulness, which is strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is really the point of luminosity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, like, on the basis of that mindfulness, your mind can get established upon luminosity, or upon all sorts of other different establishments that will kind of provide you with the same results.
[SPEAKER_01]: But isn't it obvious that it's just because for different people it works differently?
[SPEAKER_01]: I... different people can establish upon different things more successfully.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same principle of the same establishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there are the casinas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said, it's... all the different, eh... meditations... might disagree.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... the point being is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I would say it's a different exercise in regards to the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's a new... it's actually a new...
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, it's not like, for example, as I said, like the casinos, the ten casinos, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like ten casinos.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's one casino.
[SPEAKER_01]: One establishment of mind upon a casino, or one casino for an establishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, within that, you can take that same establishment, same principle, further and further and further, ten times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there are ten refinements to the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are ten casinos.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that they're laid out one, two, you go from one, then you do the next one, then you do... No, it's basically doing the same further and further and further will take you from the casino of earth to the most refined casino consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same principle, which means you don't need all ten.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you'll have all ten, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: For every jhāna, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever in the sūtra says, oh, is there beyond this?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like developing the same, how far you can go.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the practice of jhānas, the kāsinas, the establishment of different perceptions, it's always the same, same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: That principle... Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, you can... That principle is what we've been talking about in sambhāla.